[soft music]
[percussive music]
[grunting]
Yah!
[train whistle blowing]
♪ First thing we climb a tree ♪
♪ And maybe then we'd talk ♪
♪ Or sit silently ♪
♪ And listen to our thoughts ♪
♪ With illusions of someday ♪
♪ Casting a golden light ♪
♪ No dress rehearsal ♪
♪ This is our life ♪
♪ You are ahead by a century ♪
[soft music]
You'll want to hurry and eat if
you're to meet the train on time.
[sighing] I pray this
isn't foolishness...
but it's too late now.
We made a practical decision; we'll
just have to hope for the best.
With any luck, Mrs. Spencer
will have picked out a good one;
a hard worker and
obedient like we asked for.
I couldn't tolerate a
lazy boy or a sullen boy.
No, I couldn't abide it and I wouldn't.
In spite of all the
worry, I'm relieved to know
that you'll have a regular
hand about the place.
You can't buy loyalty.
You coming in sometime today?
Matthew Cuthbert, you
must be in a state.
Since when do you sit at the
table without washing your hands?
Let's not forget you were the
one convinced of this plan.
You've been set on it since winter,
so there's no point fretting now.
Not that I disagree, because I don't.
Will you be ready to set off
as soon as you're finished here?
I will.
You can bet it won't take long
for Rachel to come a-knocking.
Lord knows she's got a hunger
for gossip like a person starved.
[soft music]
[baby crying]
I told you to have their supper
on the table a half hour ago.
She needs her diaper changed, Mrs.
Hammond. The stew is almost ready.
- Did you milk the cow?
- No. Not yet, but I...
Give her to me!
You want these children
to starve to death?
Do something right for a change!
You're more trouble than you're worth.
Nothing but a miserable piece of trash!
[exclaiming] Hurry up!
We'll see what Mr. Hammond has to
say about this when he gets home.
[barking]
Are you quite all right, dear?
I like imagining
better than remembering.
Why are the worst memories
the most insistent?
I wouldn't know. Try to rest.
"If all the world hated
you and believed you wicked,
but your own conscience approved of you
and absolved you from guilt,
you would not be without friends."
I love Jane Eyre, don't you?
- I never met her.
- I'm glad you've woken.
I have so many more questions
for you about Green Gables.
I'm sure you do.
Why do you suppose neither
of the Cuthberts ever married?
Did either of them
have a tragical romance?
- It's none of our business.
- But I'm bursting with curiosity!
Uh... Shhh.
[train whistle blowing]
[soft music]
[bird peeping]
[birdsong]
- [background chatter]
- Whoa.
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
Afternoon.
Sir.
I wonder if you can
help me. Is there a...
Little girl? You didn't
see her? She's just outside.
Wouldn't come in. Darndest thing.
- But...
- Said she preferred to sit outside,
because there was... What was it now?
"More scope for the imagination."
That was it. She's a case, I should say.
I heard her talkin'
to herself out there.
But I'm not expecting a girl.
It's a boy... that I have come for.
Mrs. Spencer was to bring him
over from the asylum for us.
Mrs. Spencer got off the train
with that strange snippet,
gave her over to my charge.
Said you'd be along for her presently.
Well, that's all I know about it.
I haven't got any more
orphans concealed hereabouts.
I, uh... I don't understand.
Well, I'm sure the girl
will be only too happy
to tell you every little
detail of what happened.
She's got a tongue of her
own, that's for certain.
[chuckling] Good day to you.
I suppose you are Matthew
Cuthbert of Green Gables?
I'm very glad to see you.
I was beginning to be afraid
that you weren't coming
and I was imagining
all the things that might
have happened to prevent you.
I'd made up my mind that
if you didn't come for me,
I'd go down the tracks to
that big wild cherry tree
and climb up into it and stay all night.
I wouldn't be a bit afraid,
and it would be lovely to sleep
in a tree all white with bloom
in the moonshine, don't you think?
I can also imagine that I'm
already a disappointment to you.
I'm aware that I'm not much to look at,
but even though I'm
thin, I'm very strong.
I want you to know that I'm forever
grateful that you're adopting me.
You're a sight for
sore eyes, Mr. Cuthbert.
You best come along.
Uh - ahem - I'll take your bag.
Oh, I can carry it. It isn't heavy.
I've got all my worldly goods
in it, but it isn't heavy.
And if it isn't carried a certain way,
it falls right open,
so I better keep it.
I've come to know the exact knack of it.
I am ecstatic beyond measure
that I'm going to belong
to you and your sister.
Ecstatic! I've never
belonged to anybody before.
I mean, you and your sister are
practically the stuff of fiction.
Two hard-working, decent people,
lonely all their lives
in their silent house,
longing for the love of a child.
And I will strive to be
just the best daughter
that anybody could ever have.
I'm sure that I can do it.
To be honest, I haven't
had much experience at it.
I'm not usually brought into
a house to be a daughter,
so you can well imagine what a blessing
this is and how much my heart is lifted.
And I've given it a lot of thought,
and I am determined
that I shall be obedient,
and dutiful and yet lively enough
so as to lighten up the place
after you've lived for so many years
without the delights of a happy child
and the scope of her imagination.
Have you always wanted a daughter?
Always in your heart of hearts?
I read once that "a
daughter is a little girl"
who grows up to be a friend."
And it gives my heart a
thrill to even say it aloud.
Oh, isn't she lovely?
- What's her name?
- Uh...
that's, uh... the mare.
She doesn't have a name?
But the right name is so important.
She looks to me...
like her name is Belle.
Hello, Belle. You are a beauty,
and I am sure we'll be great friends.
- Mare.
- [clucking]
Bye, tree!
That cherry tree is my first
friend here on the Island.
What did that cherry tree, all
white and lacy, make you think of?
Well, now, um, I dunno.
Why, a bride, of course!
A bride all in white with a misty veil.
I've never seen one, but I
imagine what she would look like.
I never expect to be a bride myself.
I'm so homely, nobody
would ever want to marry me.
Unless he was a foreign missionary.
I suppose a foreign missionary
mightn't be very particular.
But I do hope someday I
shall have a white dress,
with beautiful puff sleeves.
That is my highest
ideal of earthly bliss.
Am I talking too much?
People are always telling me that I do,
and it seems to cause
no end of aggravation.
Would you rather I didn't
talk? If you say so, I'll stop.
I can stop when I make up my mind
to it, although it's difficult.
I don't mind.
I'm so glad.
I know you and I are going to
get along together just fine.
It's such a relief to
talk when one wants to
and not be told that children
should be seen and not heard.
I've had that said to me a
million times if I have once.
People would laugh at me
because I use big words.
But they're exciting
and descriptive words,
like... like "enraptured"
and "glorious"!
If you have big ideas, you have to use
big words to express them, haven't you?
Well, uh...
I suppose so.
For example:
I am enraptured by
this glorious landscape!
Careful now. Careful.
[knocking]
Afternoon, Rachel.
I've put the kettle on.
Won't you sit down?
I don't want to interrupt
if you're expecting company.
Oh, we've got plenty of time. Matthew
won't be back for several hours.
I took quite a fright when I
saw Matthew starting off today.
- I can imagine.
- Well...
I couldn't imagine what might cause him
to leave his crop in the
middle of the afternoon.
I was fearful he'd gone
to call for the doctor.
- Oh, I'm quite well.
- Oh!
What a relief. Oh, my, my, my.
[sighing] Of course, now
that I have time to think,
it wouldn't make sense for
Matthew to take the time
to put on his best set of clothes
had there been an emergency.
No... it wouldn't.
No... indeed.
Oh, for heaven's sake, Marilla.
Matthew's gone to the train
station at Bright River.
Ah. Well, well.
Bright River.
He's fetching a hired hand.
Yes and no.
We're adopting a boy
from the orphan asylum
in Nova Scotia, and he's arriving today.
Matthew's gone to fetch him.
Marilla Cuthbert,
if you had told me that
Matthew was meeting a...
kangaroo from Australia, I
couldn't be more surprised.
An orphan boy?!
What on earth put such
a notion into your head?
Because I'm gonna tell you plain:
you're doing a mighty foolish thing...
a risky thing, that's what.
[soft music]
[squawking]
I cannot believe that I'm going to
get to live somewhere so beautiful.
Dreams don't often come true, do they?
But just now I feel...
pretty nearly perfectly happy.
Although I can't feel
exactly perfectly happy,
because, well... what
colour would you call this?
It's red... isn't it?
Yes, it's red.
Now you see why I can't
be perfectly happy.
Nobody could who has red hair.
It's... my lifelong sorrow.
You don't know what you're getting.
You're letting a strange
child into your house
and you don't know a
single thing about him!
Why, only last week I
was reading in the paper
how a man and his wife
up west of the Island
took an orphan boy out of the asylum
and he set fire to their home at night!
Set it on purpose, Marilla!
And they nearly burned
to a crisp in their beds!
Now, if you would've asked
for my advice on this matter,
- which you didn't do...
- Sugar?
...I would've told
you, for mercy's sake,
not to think of such
a thing, that's what!
I don't deny there's something
in what you say, Rachel.
I've... I've had some qualms myself.
How could you not?
Matthew is getting on in years
and his heart's been bothering him.
A boy will be a great help.
And it isn't as if he's
coming from overseas
or the States. He's from Nova Scotia.
He can't be much
different than ourselves.
Well, there is some comfort in that,
knowing he's not some London street Arab
or some French ruffian.
An orphan, Marilla?
Matthew's been terrible set on it.
Well, I hope and pray
it works all right.
Only, don't say I didn't warn you
if he burns Green Gables down
or puts strychnine in the well.
I heard of a case over in New Brunswick
where an orphan-asylum
child did just that,
and the whole family
died in fearful agonies.
Only, it was a girl in that instance.
Well, we're not getting a girl.
Oh, Mr. Cuthbert!
What do they call this place?
The Avenue.
I suppose it is kind of pretty.
Pretty doesn't seem
the right word to use,
nor beautiful, either.
They don't go far enough.
It's...
wonderful.
Wonderful.
It's the first thing I
ever saw that couldn't
be improved upon by the imagination.
Other people may call it The Avenue,
but I shall always call it
the White Way of Delight.
[soft music]
This here's Barry's Pond.
Oh, I don't like that name, either.
I shall call it...
let me see...
the Lake of Shining Waters.
Yes, that's the right name for it.
I know because of the thrill.
Do things ever give you a thrill?
Well, I don't rightly know.
There has to be something.
Well, now, um...
I suppose it... kind
of gives me a thrill
to see those ugly white grubs
that spade up in the cucumber beds.
I suppose I can imagine that.
I hate the look of them.
I'd like to be rid of them.
I suppose I gave Mrs.
Hammond a thrill, then.
She was happy to be rid of
me after her husband died.
Who's Mrs. Hammond?
I worked for her family, taking
care of the children for a few years.
She had eight.
It sure seems to make some people angry
when they have so many children.
Mr. and Mrs. Hammond were
certainly vexed all the time.
[Mr. Hammond]: Move,
you little scarecrow!
[Anne]: Please, please, I...
- This'll teach ya.
- [crying]
[screaming]
- Ah!
- Mr. Hammond?!
- [barking]
- [groaning]
- Mrs. Hammond!!! Mrs. Hammond!!!
- [panting]
- [barking]
[squawking]
Is anything the matter?
No. Nothing.
I was startled by the geese, is all.
Don't you just love
them? The geese? I do.
They're a very romantical
species of bird.
Well, I wouldn't know about that.
Did you know they mate for life?
They choose each other out
of all the geese in the world,
and they stay together
until death do they part.
Well, now.
We're pretty near home.
Just another mile or so.
Home.
What a wonderful word.
Green Gables.
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
I've pinched myself so many times today.
Every little while, this horrible,
sickening feeling would come over me,
and I'd be so afraid
that this was all a dream.
But I just had to one more time.
This is real.
Green Gables is real and we're home.
- Mare.
- [clucking]
[soft music]
Matthew Cuthbert, who's that?
Where is the boy?
There wasn't any boy.
There was only her.
No boy? But there must've been a boy.
We sent word to Mrs.
Spencer to bring us a boy.
Well, she didn't.
She brought her.
I asked the stationmaster.
I had to bring her home.
She couldn't be left there,
no matter where the mistake had come in.
Well, this is a pretty
piece of business.
She's got to go back.
You don't want me.
I should've expected it.
I might've known nobody
would really want me.
Oh, for heaven's sake, child,
what are you doing on the ground?
Now, you listen here and stand up.
- What do you make of this?
- I, uh...
I figure...
she's traveled a long
way to be disappointed.
Well, she shouldn't be here.
You should never have brought her home.
[distantly]: She's had a shock.
[distantly]: She's not the only one.
Enough of this foolishness.
[distantly]: Come along inside.
I'm speaking to you, child.
Little girl, that's enough now.
Little girl.
Little girl!
Little girl?
I wish I was anything but.
There's no point in crying.
There's been a mistake, is all.
We're not going to turn
you out-of-doors tonight.
What is your name?
What does it matter?
I won't be here long
enough for you to remember.
You will mind your manners
and answer the question.
Please... call me Cordelia.
Call you Cordelia? Is that your name?
Or Penelope.
Penelope has a very tragical ring to it.
What is your name, child?
Couldn't you call me either of those?
My name is Anne.
Plain Anne.
Anne is a fine name.
A sensible name.
Could you please spell it
with an E when you speak it?
Anne with an E looks
much more distinguished.
Very well, then,
Anne with an E,
it's time to come inside.
Get yourself up now.
[birdsong]
I knew it.
This is a lovely home.
Why didn't you tell me at the train
station that you didn't want me?
Why didn't you just leave me there?
If I hadn't seen the
White Way of Delight
or the Lake of Shining Waters,
this wouldn't be so hard.
What on earth does she mean?
It's just a conversation...
we had on the road.
I'll put the mare in.
[Marilla sighing] Take off your hat.
Lay it and your bag on the bench.
I simply don't understand.
Were there no boys at the asylum?
There was an abundance of them.
But Mrs. Spencer said distinctly
that you wanted a girl about my age,
and the matron thought that I would do.
This is what comes of sending
word and not going ourselves.
Follow me. Don't dally.
I'm sorry to disappoint you,
but there's nothing to be done.
We want a boy to help
Matthew with the farm work.
A girl would be of no use
to us. Do you understand?
- I can't say that I do.
- I beg your pardon?
I don't mean any disrespect, but
couldn't I do the farm
chores even though I'm a girl?
That's not the way of
things and you know it.
But couldn't I? I'm as strong as a boy,
and I prefer to be outdoors
instead of cooped up in a kitchen.
I don't understand the conundrum.
For example, what if, suddenly,
there were no boys in
the world, none at all...
Fiddlesticks.
It doesn't make sense that girls
aren't allowed to do farm work
when girls can do anything
a boy can do and more!
Do you consider yourself to
be delicate and incapable?
Because I certainly don't.
Anyway, since I'm here now,
couldn't you consider it?
I could not. And put those
fool notions out of your head.
Now come along. Let's get
you washed up for supper.
Oh, good gracious, child,
what's happened here?
I was pinching myself a lot today,
to prove that this was all true.
You're not eating at all.
I can't.
I'm sorry.
I'm in the depths of despair.
Can you eat when you're
in the depths of despair?
I've never been in the depths
of despair, so I can't say.
Well, did you ever imagine that
you were in the depths of despair?
No, I didn't.
It's a very uncomfortable
feeling indeed.
When you try to eat, a big lump
comes right up into your throat,
and you can't swallow anything,
not even if it was a chocolate caramel.
I had chocolate caramel once, two
years ago, and it was simply delicious.
I hope you won't be
offended that I can't eat.
Everything is extremely nice.
I guess she's just tired.
Best put her to bed.
Fetch your bag and follow me.
[sighing]
[door creaking]
[soft music]
Undress, quick as you can, get to bed.
I'll come back in a few
minutes for the candle.
[panting and sniffling]
[crying]
[sobbing]
Good night.
How can you call it a good night
when you know this must be the
very worst night I've ever had?
[sobbing]
Oh, that is a filthy habit.
I dare say a man's
got a right to smoke...
when his mind's burdened.
I dare say yours is, too.
Yes, this is certainly
a fine kettle of fish.
One of us will have to drive over
and see Mrs. Spencer
tomorrow, that's for certain.
The girl will have to be sent back.
Yup, I suppose so.
You suppose so? Don't you know it?
Well, it...
seems a pity
to send her back.
She's so set on staying.
Matthew Cuthbert, do you mean to
say you think we ought to keep her?!
No, no, I-I-I-I...
No, I suppose not.
I should say not.
What good would she be to us?
We might be some good to her.
I believe that child has bewitched you.
I can see it plain as
plain you want to keep her.
She's a real interesting kind of person.
That's one way to put it.
You should've heard her
talk coming from the station.
She can talk fast enough and
it's nothing in her favour.
I don't mind the conversation.
I don't like children
who have so much to say.
There's something I don't
understand about her.
No, she's got to be dispatched
straight way back where she came from.
I could hire a boy to help me and, uh...
she could be company for you.
I'm not suffering for company.
And I'm not gonna keep her.
Well, now, it's just as you say...
of course.
I'm going to bed.
[Anne crying]
[crickets chirring]
[trilling]
[sobbing]
[birdsong]
[rooster crowing]
[soft music]
Dearest Snow Queen,
I accept your token offering.
Had I a book,
I would press these sacred
blossoms between its pages
so that I could forever be
reminded of this treasured moment.
Nevertheless...
...I...
Princess Cordelia...
...shall cherish this gift always.
Let my kiss prove my devotion...
- [door opens]
- What are you doing?
It's time you were dressed.
I was imagining that this morning
was different than what it is.
I was making believe that...
I was a beautiful princess
and this was my sacred chamber,
high in a tall stone spire...
Never mind your chatter.
I'm sorry.
It's just that your gable room
and your lovely old cherry tree
provide such scope for the imagination.
I've... also been wishing
with all my might that you'd tell me
that you'd decided that I could stay.
Pack that inside and come downstairs.
We'll be driving to see
Mrs. Spencer after breakfast.
[soft music]
Put that down at once!
- Did you take anything?
- No!
I was only memorizing.
Let me see.
Stop your snooping
and come to breakfast.
I'm pretty hungry this morning.
The world doesn't seem such a howling
wilderness as it did last night.
I'm glad it's a pretty morning so
we won't be driving back in the rain.
That would be extremely
difficult to bear.
It's all very well to...
read sorrowful stories
and imagine yourself living
through them heroically, but...
it's not so easy when you're
actually woeful, is it?
For pity's sake, hold your tongue.
You talk entirely too much.
Yes, ma'am.
Just so's you know, I sent
word to see if that French boy
is available through harvest.
- Gracious me!
- I can milk a cow and split wood!
I can wash clothes, iron, dust,
sweep and so many other things!
There's no end to what I could
accomplish given the chance.
I'll take care of these
dishes for you, Miss Cuthbert.
You will see, I'll do them right.
Be careful with the kettle.
It's very hot. Use both hands.
I see it clear now:
this very idea was folly.
You can't make up a family.
Only kin is kin.
[thunder rumbling]
Surely you'll be needing...
Anne more than ever since
your husband's passing.
I don't want her.
I'm moving to mysister's and
I got no reason to take her.
I'm sorry, but we're
overcrowded as it is.
- I don't need another mouth to feed.
- [Anne]: But I can help you.
Haven't I been of help to you?
Please don't leave me here.
You're not kin. I got enough kin.
You're taking her back and that's final.
[thunder]
[utensils falling]
I'm so sorry! Nothing's broken.
Oh, you'll never keep me now.
I was never going to keep you.
I'll be back in time for tea.
Anne...
Goodbye, Mr. Cuthbert.
I, uh... didn't say I'd hire a boy
to be rid of you.
It was in hopes that you could stay.
Thank you.
I'll never forget you.
You take care now...
...Anne with an E.
Oh, for heaven's sake.
[clucking]
My brother is a ridiculous man.
I think he's lovely.
He's ever so sympathetic,
and he didn't seem to
mind how much I talked.
In fact, he seemed to like it.
I felt he was a kindred spirit
as soon as ever I saw him.
You're both queer enough,
that's for sure and certain.
I've made up my mind
to enjoy this drive.
It's been my experience that you
can nearly always enjoy something
if you make up your mind
firmly that you will.
Of course, you must
make up your mind firmly.
I believe this is something
you and I have in common.
[seagulls squawking]
I wish I was a seagull. They're
the most carefree of all the birds,
don't you think?
Look.
Wild roses! Isn't pink just
the most bewitching colour?
I love it, but I can't wear it.
Redheaded people can't wear
pink, not even in the imagination.
Do you know of anybody whose
hair was red when she was young,
but got to be another
colour when she grew up?
I shouldn't think it likely.
There's another hope gone.
"My life is a perfect
graveyard of buried hopes."
I read that sentence in a book once,
and I say it to comfort myself
whenever I'm disappointed in anything.
Don't see where the
comforting comes in, myself.
Because it sounds so romantic,
as if I were a heroine in a storybook.
- You must've gone to school.
- Not a great deal,
although I went recently
when I was back at the asylum.
I love school, but when I'm in a
household with so much to attend to,
the children and the cooking and
the chores, it just wasn't an option.
Is there a reason why
Green Gables is so secluded?
A reason?
My family wasn't inclined
toward idle chatter.
Do you miss your parents terribly?
They lived good, Christian lives.
You can't begrudge God
for bringing them home.
I suppose not.
You suppose not?!
Why is it you find yourself an orphan?
It happened when I was an infant.
I'd like to know the circumstances,
if you've a mind to tell them.
I don't mind telling stories.
"Somewhere in a far-off land,
in a place whose name I
do not care to remember,
a gentleman lived not long ago,
one of those with a lance
and ancient shield on a shelf
who keeps a skinny nag and
a greyhound for racing..."
How dare you?
- What?
- Do you take me for a fool?
It's just it's a much
better story than mine.
I didn't ask for any
story, I asked for yours.
If you can't tell the truth,
then I have no time for you.
If you'll let me tell you
what I imagine about myself,
you'll find it ever so
much more interesting.
Wishing something is different
than it is will not make it so.
Truer words were never spoken.
My parents were Walter
and Bertha Shirley.
They were newlyweds, and
they were poor as church mice.
They died of a fever when
I was three months old.
So I've been earning my keep
for as long as I can remember.
And... I suppose I was
lucky that I was placed out
instead of staying in the asylum.
I never understood it.
If children are such a burden, then
why do people have so many of them?
Nevertheless... it's a shame
I'll never have the opportunity.
What do you mean?
To be one.
- [neighing]
- Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa!
- Ah!
- [barking]
Anne!
No! Go home!
Go home!
[whimpering]
Oh, my Lord!
Are you all right?
- Shhh.
- Oh, dear Lord!
- I'm fine. Here you are.
- Oh, oh, oh, oh.
Shhh. It's all right.
It's all right, Belle.
There's no need to worry anymore, Belle.
- Belle?
- That's her name.
Wasn't that an adventure?
Wasn't it just.
[Anne laughing]
- You're sure you're all right?
- Mm-hmm.
Oh.
You were very level-headed.
I'm used to a ruckus.
[clicking]
- Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
- [Belle chuffing]
My, my, you're the last
folks I was looking for today,
but I'm real glad to see you.
And how are you doing, dear Anne?
I'm well enough, thank you.
What brings you by, Miss Cuthbert?
The fact is, Mrs. Spencer,
there's been a queer mistake somewhere
and I've come over to see where it is.
Matthew and I sent word for you
to bring us a boy from the asylum.
We told your brother Robert
to tell you we wanted a boy.
Marilla Cuthbert, you don't say so.
Why, Robert sent word through his
daughter Nancy
that you wanted a girl.
Oh, that Nancy is a
terrible flighty thing.
I've often had to scold
her for her heedlessness.
I'm dreadfully sorry about this.
It was our own fault.
We should've come to you ourselves,
and not left an important message
to be handed along by word of mouth.
However, the mistake has been made and
the only thing to do is to set it right.
I suppose the asylum will
take her back, won't they?
I suppose.
But it might not be
necessary to return her.
My neighbour, Mrs. Blewett,
was just saying to me
she's overburdened by her large family
and she wishes she'd
sent for a girl to help.
Anne will do nicely.
I call this positively providential.
We'll call on her and
see. I'm sure she'll agree.
[crying]
How old are you and what's your name?
Anne Shirley. I'm just 13.
Hmm. You don't look as if there's
much to you. But you're wiry.
I dunno, but the wiry ones
are the best after all.
If I take you, you'll do as I
say and speak when spoken to.
I don't suffer no backtalk,
and if I find you lacking,
you'll know the toe of my boot.
I expect you to earn
your keep, and no mistake.
I'm at my wits' end with this
one. He'll be the death of me.
[wailing]
That's a colic cry.
What?
He'll do better if you swaddle him.
And... gripe water helps.
Anne has worked for
large families before.
And work she will. This
ain't no charity house.
Well, I suppose I can take her
off your hands, Miss Cuthbert.
If you like, I can take her right now.
Well, I... I don't know. I...
I didn't say Matthew and I
had absolutely decided
we wouldn't keep her.
I just came over to find out
how the mistake had occurred.
I'd better take her home again
and talk it over with my brother.
I ought not to decide on
anything without consulting him.
If we make up our minds not to keep
her, we'll send her over to you.
Otherwise, you can assume
that she'll be staying with us.
Will that suit you, Mrs. Blewett?
- I suppose it'll have to.
- Very well.
- [baby crying]
- Good day.
- [crying]
- [barking]
Oh, Miss Cuthbert,
did you really just say
that perhaps you'd let
me stay at Green Gables,
or did I only imagine that you did?
Yes, I did say that and no more.
But it isn't decided yet
and perhaps we'll conclude
that Mrs. Blewett should
take you after all.
I'd rather go back to the
asylum than live with her.
I keep expecting her to chase
after us on a broomstick.
I would like you to hold
your tongue on the ride home.
I've got plenty to think about.
[whinnying]
[soft music]
I'll thank you to keep
your questions to yourself
until we can speak in private.
Run along inside.
Put your bag upstairs
and put the kettle on.
Yes, Miss Cuthbert.
Wipe that silly grin off your face.
I wouldn't give a dog I
liked to that Blewett woman.
Trouble is, I don't
know about keeping her.
She's an interesting little thing.
More to the point if she
was a useful little thing.
I propose we give her a one-week
trial to see how she behaves.
She has five days.
I'll need a lot of
convincing, that's for certain.
[cow lowing]
Oh, for Heaven's sake.
- [crickets chirring]
- [owl hooting]
I noticed last night that
you threw your clothes
all about the floor
when you took them off.
That is a very untidy
habit and I can't allow it.
You must fold your clothing
neatly and place it on the chair.
I haven't any use for
little girls who aren't neat.
I was so harrowed up
in my mind last night,
I didn't think about my clothes at all.
I'll fold them nicely tonight.
Although I have been known to forget.
I'm usually in such a
hurry to finally get to bed.
Well, you'll have to remember
if you're going to stay here.
You understand that
you're on trial, yes?
Yes.
A decision will be made in one week.
Now... say your prayers
and get into bed.
I never say any prayers.
What?!
I said them at the asylum Sunday school.
I liked the catechism.
There's something splendid
about some of the words,
"infinite and unchangeable."
It's not quite poetry, but it
sounds a lot like it, doesn't it?
We're not talking about poetry,
Anne, we're talking about prayers!
Don't you know it's a
terrible wicked thing
not to say your prayers every night?
I'm sorry, I was never
taught to say them.
You must say your prayers
while you're under my roof.
Of course, if you want me to.
I'd do anything to oblige you.
But you'll have to tell me how
to say them for just this once.
You must kneel down.
Why must people kneel down to pray?
If I really wanted to pray,
I'll tell you what I'd do.
I'd go into a great big field,
all alone,
or into the deep, deep woods,
and I'd look up into the sky, up-up-up,
into that lovely blue sky without end,
and I would just feel a prayer.
Well, I'm ready.
What am I to say?
You're old enough to pray for yourself.
Just... thank God for your blessings
and ask Him humbly for
the things that you want.
I'll do my best.
[sighing] Gracious heavenly Father...
That's what ministers say in church,
so I suppose it's all
right for private prayer?
Gracious heavenly Father...
...I thank Thee for
the White Way of Delight
and the Lake of Shining Waters,
and for dear Belle,
and the lovely Snow Queen.
I'm really extremely grateful for them.
And that's all the blessings I can
think of just now to thank Thee for.
And as for things I
want, they're so numerous
that it would take me a great
deal of time to name them all,
so I shall only mention
the two most important.
Please let me stay at Green Gables,
please let me be
good-looking when I grow up.
Yours respectfully, Anne Shirley.
There.
Did I do it all right?
That'll do for now.
Get into bed, child.
Oh! I just realized I
should've said "Amen"
in place of "yours respectfully"
the way ministers do?
Do you suppose it'll
make any difference?
- I don't suppose it will.
- As God is my witness,
I will do everything in my earthly power
to make you want to keep me.
Good night.
God, give me strength
to succeed in my quest!
- That will do.
- Sorry.
I quite like praying.
Well, it's time to say good night.
Good night.
[sighing]
That girl's next door
to a perfect heathen.
God only knows what we're
getting ourselves into.
[rooster crowing]
[cattle lowing]
Anne?!
Anne!
She's gone!
- Gone?
- I'll check the silverware.
[clucking]
Eggs! That's one chore done!
Now I've met all the chickens,
so you don't need to
make any introductions!
I've been up since before the sun.
I was too excited to sleep.
And I wanted to start proving
to you that I should stay.
It's so easy to love
Green Gables, isn't it?
I'll let the milkers out to graze.
I'll have breakfast on soon.
May I take these blossoms up to my room?
No.
You don't want your room or your
person cluttered up with flowers.
You should've left them on
the tree in the first place.
I felt a little that way, too.
I felt I shouldn't shorten their
lovely lives by picking them.
I mean, I wouldn't want to
be picked if I were a blossom.
Wouldn't it be lovely to be a blossom?
Yesterday, you wanted to be a seagull.
And the power and the glory forever.
Amen. [laughing]
I like this prayer.
It's lovely.
Our Father, who art in heaven,
hallowed be Thy name!
It's like a line of music.
Just get on with the
business of learning it.
"Our Father, who art in heaven"...
Regardless of the outcome here,
you should have something to wear
besides that flimsy bit of business.
I have a leftover piece of cotton
on a bolt that may do nicely.
You're going to make me a dress?
You need something
suitable that fits you.
A new dress! I've never
had a new dress. Not ever.
I can't wait to have puff
sleeves and ever so many flounces!
Do you think you can adorn it with
lace at the cuff and neckline, too?
I don't believe in frills or flounces.
But surely you don't mind puff
sleeves? All the girls are wearing them.
Puff sleeves are divine.
Waste of fabric.
Oh.
Well, I'm sure if it's a lovely
azure blue or willow green,
I'm sure I won't mind if it's...
plain.
You're a vain one and no mistake.
Brown is a very sensible colour.
I'll need your dress so I
can use it for a pattern.
Let's take these things off now.
Thank you, Miss Cuthbert.
I'm very grateful to have
something new, really I am.
I'm sure I can imagine it's fashionable.
It shouldn't take me about a day or two.
If it looks just like this one,
it shouldn't take you any time at all.
You run along now, and learn the prayer.
Yes, Miss Cuthbert.
"Our Father, who art in
heaven, hallowed be..."
Puff sleeves!
Good morning, Marilla.
Good morning, Rachel.
I brought you some scones.
I felt sure you wouldn't
have time for baking,
- what with all the hubbub.
- Thank you.
I'll just come in and
sit a spell, shall I?
Catch my breath.
I've been hearing some surprising
things about you and Matthew.
I don't suppose you're any
more surprised than I am myself.
What an incredible mistake.
The mind reels.
Couldn't you have just sent her back?
We may yet,
but for now, she's here on trial.
Trial?
One week.
Matthew is quite set on keeping her.
And I'll admit she's
a bright little thing.
But I'll need a great
deal more convincing.
I know it by heart, Miss Cuthbert!
Anne, this is our neighbour, Mrs. Lynde.
Well, they didn't pick
you for your looks,
that's sure and certain.
She's terribly skinny
and homely, Marilla.
[Rachel chuckling]
All elbows and knees. [laughing]
And did you ever see such freckles?
And hair as red as
carrots. Dear, dear me.
I hate you.
- Anne.
- I hate you. I hate you, I hate you!!
- Anne!
- How dare you call me skinny and ugly?!
How dare you call me
freckled and redheaded?!
- You are a rude, unfeeling woman!
- Well!
How would you like to have
such things said about you?!
How would you like to be told
that you're fat and clumsy
and probably hadn't a spark
of imagination in you?!
And I don't care if I hurt
your feelings by saying so.
I hope I hurt them!
Because you have hurt my feelings
worse than they have
ever been hurt before,
and I will never forgive
you for this! Never, never!!!
Anne!
Come back here!
Well...
I never.
It's a good thing you can send her back.
I wouldn't envy you the
job of bringing that up.
You shouldn't have twitted
her about her looks, Rachel.
Marilla Cuthbert...
...you don't mean to tell
me that you are upholding her
in such a terrible display
of temper as we've just seen?
I am not trying to excuse
her. She has been very naughty,
and I'll have to give
her a talking-to about it.
But we must make allowances for her.
She's never been taught what is right.
And you were too hard on her, Rachel.
Well...
I can see now
I'm going to have to be very
careful what I say after this
since the fine feelings of orphans,
brought from goodness knows where,
have to be considered
before anything else.
- Now, now...
- Oh, no, no.
I'm not vexed.
Don't worry yourself.
I feel too sorry for you to
have any anger left in my mind.
But if you will take my advice
you will have that "talking-to"
with a fair-sized birch switch,
and get her on the next train out.
Goodbye, Marilla.
[panting]
[seagulls squawking]
It's been quite a swell.
She'll make her own way home.
I could go...
She's in her under things,
so she's gotta come back.
The girl needs to learn some sense.
I'm sorry.
I shouldn't have lost my temper and
embarrassed you in front of Mrs. Lynde.
- I hope you can forgive me.
- Are you all right?
- Yes.
- I'm sorry for worrying you.
I needed time to ponder.
If you let me stay, I'll do my very best
not to fly into another
temper ever again.
I appreciate that you're contrite, Anne,
but the person that you owe
the apology to is Mrs. Lynde.
But she hadn't any right to
call me ugly and redheaded!
You say it yourself often enough.
But there's such a
difference between saying
a thing yourself and
hearing other people say it!
You need to learn discipline.
Just magine how you would
feel if someone told you
to your face that you
were skinny and ugly.
Remember when we were young,
Marilla, and old lady Adams said...
- Yes.
- You were gawky...
Yes. Thank you. I recall
you suffered from it.
I don't say that Mrs. Lynde was exactly
right in saying what
she did to you, Anne.
- She's too outspoken...
- She's a bully.
But that is no excuse for
such behaviour on your part.
You were rude and saucy and
you must go to Mrs. Lynde
and tell her that you're sorry
and ask her to forgive you.
I could never do that.
Punish me any way you like.
Shut me up in a dark, damp
dungeon and I shan't complain,
but I cannot ask Mrs.
Lynde to forgive me!
We're not in the habit of
shutting people up in dungeons.
But apologize to Mrs. Lynde you must.
And you'll stay up in your room
until you can tell me that
you're willing to do it.
I'll have to stay up
there forever, then,
because I can't tell Mrs. Lynde I'm
sorry I said those things to her.
How can I?
I'm not sorry.
I'm sorry I vexed you,
but I'm glad I told her just what I did.
It was a great satisfaction.
In fact, I can't even imagine...
that I'm sorry.
Well, let's hope your imagination
is in better working order by morning.
You can't send her back over this.
Don't be so sure.
Oh, it's...
it's good that, uh...
Rachel got a calling-down.
Wish I'd been there.
Matthew Cuthbert, I'm astonished at you.
And you'll take her up a meal?
When did you ever hear of me
starving people into good behaviour?
But she'll stay up there until she's
willing to apologize and that is final!
[crickets chirring]
[soft music]
[seagulls squawking]
[crickets chirring]
[soft music]
How's by you, Anne?
I'm fairly well, thank you.
I imagine a good deal, so
that helps pass the time.
Don't you think you'd
better... say it... and just...
have it over with?
If I apologize, I'll be fibbing.
Hmm.
It'll have to be done...
sooner or later,
for Marilla's a...
a dreadful determined woman.
Dreadful determined.
So am I.
It's, uh...
it's terrible lonesome downstairs...
without you.
I'm not used to the quiet anymore.
The trouble is, the
prospect seems humiliating.
And unfair.
But you're smart enough...
...to find the right
words, I'm sure of it.
But why should the apology
have to come from me
when it was Mrs. Lynde who
caused the entire situation?
Well, you know...
I like to think that...
...that one fine day,
it won't matter a whit to you
what anybody says sideways.
You have a good imagination.
I suppose it would be true
enough to say I'm sorry.
I am sorry I upset Miss Marilla.
And you.
So go and smooth things over, can't you?
Very well. I'll attempt it.
For you.
Now, that's good news.
Don't tell Marilla
we had a conversation,
on account of we decided
raising you was her department.
I shall carry our secret to my grave.
[birdsong]
Whatever are you thinking, Anne,
I hope you're taking this seriously.
Oh, I am.
I'm imagining out what
I must say to Mrs. Lynde.
Oh, Mrs. Lynde, I am so extremely sorry!
I could never express my sorrow, no,
not even if I used
up a whole dictionary.
I behaved terribly to you,
and I've disgraced my
dear friends the Cuthberts,
who may let me stay at Green
Gables even though I'm not a boy!
I am a dreadfully wicked
and ungrateful girl,
and I deserve to be punished and
cast out by respectable society forever!
It was awful of me to fly into a temper
because you told me the truth.
And it was the truth. Every
word you said was true.
My hair is red and I am
freckled and skinny and ugly!
Now, what I said to you was true,
too, but I shouldn't have said it!
Oh, Mrs. Lynde, please,
please say you can forgive me!
If you refuse,
oh, it'll be a lifelong sorrow
on a poor little orphan girl.
Please say you forgive me, Mrs. Lynde!
There, there. Get up, child.
Of course I forgive you.
I guess I was a little hard on you,
but I'm just an outspoken person.
You mustn't mind me, that's what I say.
Thank you for your kind consideration.
I look forward to never
minding what you say again.
Indeed.
Although it can't be denied
your hair is terrible red.
But there may be hope for it.
There was a girl in
our class who had hair
every bit as red as yours.
Do you recall, Marilla?
But when she grew up,
it darkened to a real handsome auburn.
I wouldn't be a mite
surprised if yours did, too.
Oh, Mrs. Lynde, you've given me hope!
I shall always remember
that you are a benefactor...
We should run along, Rachel.
Thank you for your graciousness.
Of course.
She has a queer way
of expressing herself.
Forcible-like.
I apologized pretty well, didn't I?
I thought since I had to do it,
I might as well do it thoroughly.
You did it thoroughly, all right.
I hope you'll try to control
your temper better in the future.
I will. I absolutely will.
Although apologizing is
my new favourite thing.
[laughing]
I'm going to prove myself
worthy of staying, Miss Cuthbert.
I've been making a list in my head
of all the ways I might
be useful to you both.
And in addition to the indoor chores,
I'm sure I can help with
the outdoor chores, too.
I'm much stronger than
I look. It isn't too...
You hired a boy?
But I haven't even
finished my trial yet.
There's work needs
to be done either way.
How long will you be here?
Allô. You must be Anne.
- With an E.
- Je m'appelle Jerry.
Jerry Baynard. Nice to meet you.
Baynard. Foolhardy.
Pardon?
Your surname means
reckless or foolhardy.
Charlemagne even named his
impossible horse Baynard.
I don't know him... Charlemagne.
Of course you don't. He
died hundreds of years ago.
- So you living here now?
- Yes.
Probably. I... I don't know!
Pretty here.
You're lucky.
I don't remember you
from the orphanage...
No, no, I live in town. Big family.
We have a small shop,
but with so many...
some of us must work.
Well, if you come from
such a large family,
it may trouble your conscience
to know that you are
displacing my own position
in my very first potential family.
I am hired through harvest, so...
I don't think the Cuthberts
will need you if I stay.
In fact, if you hand me your pitchfork,
I'll be happy to finish your task.
- What's your problem?
- You.
You're my problem.
All I'm doing is my job.
What are you supposed to be doing?
[coughing]
My apology was an unmitigated success.
Mrs. Lynde was very pleased.
It's not Rachel Lynde that
you need to worry about.
Well, Miss Cuthbert seemed pleased, too.
Now you're talking.
It'll ease Marilla's mind...
that I've got help.
Matthew... are you sure
you still want me to stay?
The thing of it is,
and Marilla won't admit this,
but she's getting older, too.
I'll go right in!
That's a good idea.
Hey, hey.
- Good day to you, Matthew.
- William.
Checking the perimeter?
Anything I should know about?
I wanted to talk to you
about your new... acquisition.
New?
The orphan girl from Nova Scotia.
Word in town has it that
you're keeping the girl.
Well...
we're pretty well decided,
that's true enough.
I wonder if Marilla and
the girl could come to call.
Her name's Anne.
The girl.
And that's... that's
real neighbourly of you.
Uh, I'm guessing that
she and your Diana...
they're about the same age.
Before we permit our children
to associate with your "Anne,"
my wife and I need to assure ourselves
that she won't corrupt
their good natures
or exert any negative influence.
I'm sure you can understand.
Oh, I... I understand.
Very good.
- Afternoon tea tomorrow?
- Tea tomorrow.
Excellent. Good day to you.
You've got an invitation to tea...
tomorrow afternoon.
Barry's.
They want to meet Anne.
I haven't finished the dress.
She can't go wearing
that. Oh, my heavens.
Who are the Barrys and why
do they want to meet me?
Our neighbours. A very
respectable family.
Hem. Buttons. You'll want
to be on your best behaviour.
But why?
They have two little
girls who are very well-mannered.
Do they... need help?
Diana is the girl...
- nearest your age.
- If you stay here,
perhaps you two will become friends.
A real friend.
Let go! Let go of me!
- Shut it! I mean it.
- [panting]
[whimpering]
Go get it.
- Hold her down.
- Please... don't! Don't!
Stop talking.
Guess what, Princess Cordelia.
We're sick of you and
your stupid stories!
- Stupid stories!
- Liar!
[squealing]
This little mousey made too much noise.
- Squeak squeak squeak...
But then it got caught in a trap.
So now... no more squeaking.
So shut your face from now on.
- Let's go.
- [laughter]
I'm so sorry.
Speak only when spoken to.
No startling speeches.
Anne? What's wrong?
Are you ill?
No, Miss Cuthbert.
I'm fine. Don't worry.
I'll be quiet as a mouse.
Um, I don't feel
nearly as squashed in it
as I did in my old one.
High praise indeed.
You've got room to grow.
It's so nice to be
wearing something new,
I don't even mind not
having puff sleeves.
This was mine as a girl,
so it's far from new...
but it'll do nicely.
Thank you.
It's so pretty.
You look clean and tidy,
and that's what counts.
- Isn't this lovely.
- Hand it here.
- May I try it on?
- That is not a toy.
This is a treasured possession.
- Do you understand?
- I completely understand.
Amethyst is my favourite.
I think diamonds pale in comparison.
Do you now?
Amethysts are so much more romantic.
This was my grandmother's.
My mother bequeathed it to me.
Well, it's perfectly elegant.
Are you ready to go?
- I'm not sure.
- What do you mean?
It's just... this is a meeting
of great auspiciousness.
What if she doesn't like me?
It's her mother you've
got to reckon with.
If Mrs. Barry doesn't like you,
it won't matter a wit
how much Diana does.
Whatever is the matter with you, child?
You haven't said a word since
we left. You're not yourself.
Perfect.
Good afternoon, Miss Cuthbert.
Afternoon, Mrs. Barry.
Please, call me Eliza.
And... this must be Anne.
Good afternoon.
Afternoon.
Thank you for having us, Eliza.
Marilla, Anne,
please come in.
I don't believe you said
two words during tea.
You didn't even remark on the cake.
Mother let me help her bake it special.
You enjoyed it...
didn't you?
The cake was scrumptious.
Scrumptious. [chuckling]
Have you always been shy,
or does it come from being an orphan?
I'm less shy than reticent.
Goodness, there's another 25-cent word.
It's just...
Yes?
I like to read. When I can.
I like reading, too,
but Mother prefers
that I do needlepoint.
Does needlepoint provide much
scope for the imagination?
I don't think imagination
is my strong suit.
Really?
I don't know what I'd do without mine.
Life would be an agony.
An utter... agony.
Agony. [chuckling]
I make up stories all the time.
I could never do that.
I like to imagine that I
am a princess in a tower.
Or Joan of Arc riding into battle!
Or a forlorn bride who lives by the sea
but never speaks to anyone,
because her one true love was lost
when his ship went down and disappeared
beneath the waves!
[Anne laughing]
Wonderful. Could you
tell me a story now?
- I could tell you 12!
- [laughter]
Diana...
do you think you could
like me just... a little?
I already do.
Shall we swear to be best
friends forever and ever?
It's dreadfully wicked to swear.
No, it's not my kind of
swearing. There are two kinds.
I know because I have a worldly outlook.
This kind isn't wicked at all.
It means vowing and promising solemnly.
I swear it does.
See?
- How do you do it?
- Well...
This ought to be done by
moonlight or over running water,
but we'll just imagine
that it's night time
and that this path is a stream.
Hold this...
and twist your pinky finger around mine.
I'll repeat the oath first.
I solemnly swear...
to be faithful to my
bosom friend, Diana Barry,
for as long as the sun
and moon shall endure.
And then she said it and put my name in.
And then we sent our
oath into the world.
Not in the...
- [Marilla sighing.]
- Sorry. I'll collect them.
It was a wonderful
afternoon! I'm so relieved!
It seems you made a favorable
impression with the Barrys.
And Diana didn't mind my stories at all.
In fact, I told her two,
and we promised to make up another
the next time we're together.
Diana says she doesn't
have much imagination,
but I don't think it matters,
since I have enough for both of us.
They're hosting a church picnic next week
at the Lake of Shining Waters.
I've never been to a picnic.
Can we go, Miss Cuthbert?
[sighing] We'll see.
Diana and I are kindred spirits.
And I think she'd be struck quite
sad if I were to be sent away.
Please take my shawl upstairs
and lay it neatly on my chair.
May I go outside after and
help Matthew with the cattle?
I can't wait to tell him everything!
As long as you're helping and
not just flapping your gums.
[soft, enchanting music]
I'm sorry to arrive so late to
the ball, dear Prince Wisteria.
One of my squires returned on
horseback after a harrowing journey...
and handed me a letter...
that required my urgent attention.
So please, do not doubt my love.
...and please, please let the
Cuthberts decide to keep me.
I realize now it's the
only thing I truly want,
so you don't have to worry
yourself about my red hair.
[chuckling] Amen.
Where is my brooch?
- It should be there on your shawl.
- It is not.
Nor is it in my jewellery box.
Did you take it?
I was playing with it,
but I didn't take it.
- You were told not to touch it.
- I'm sorry.
It's just it's so
beautiful, I couldn't resist.
You were told to set
the shawl on the chair.
I did.
I've looked everywhere and the
brooch is nowhere to be found.
[sighing] Give it back.
Right now.
But I didn't take it, Miss Cuthbert.
Honest, I didn't.
I don't believe you.
Where else would it be?
Confess at once.
But I...
I'm not going to live
with a thief under my roof.
You confess to stealing the brooch,
or you have no future
here at Green Gables.
- But I didn't take it.
- Confess.
Or I'll send you right
back to the asylum.
If I don't confess...
you'll send me back?
Confess to what you have done.
If I do, can I stay
here at Green Gables?
Did you, or did you
not, take the brooch?
I lost it. I... I was...
I was playing Lady Cordelia when
I took the brooch outside with me.
As I was drawing water from the well,
I leaned over to make
a wish and it fell in.
I heard it make a splash as it
disappeared down into the depths.
I'm ever so sorry, Miss Cuthbert.
Pack your things.
But you said if I
confessed I could stay!
I told you that brooch
meant a great deal to me.
No, b-b-but I made it up!
None of that was real!
I didn't take your brooch!
I don't know where it is!
Please, Miss Cuthbert,
you have to believe me!
I don't have to do anything.
Please, Miss Cuthbert...
I can't trust one
word out of your mouth.
- Please...
- Enough.
You're not to leave this room tonight.
Tomorrow, you will go... at first light.
[soft music]
Matthew!
Yah! Yah!
Yah! Giddy-up!
[soft, dramatic music]
Yah!
[whistle blowing]
[soft, dramatic music]
[whinnying]
Did I miss it? Did I miss the train?
Not to worry, your
girl got on all right.
[train whistle in the distance]
[mournful music]
[soft music]
[music fading]
[train whistle blowing]
Synced and corrected by louvette
www.addic7ed.com
Announcer: On the next
brand-new episode of Anne...
She's no longer in residence.
She has to be here.
So if you wouldn't mind
conveying me towards my new life.
What if something horrible
has happened and it's my fault?
I am my own family now. I am all I need.
Announcer: Anne,
Sunday April 2nd at 8:00 on CBC.
Narrator: James Wolfe is set
to storm the city of Quebec.
Announcer:
Canada: The Story of Us,
special two hour series premier,
Sunday, March 26th
at 8:00 on CBC.